A Guide to the Nell Blaine Papers, 1945-1999, undated
Virginia Commonwealth University, James Branch Cabell Library
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library
Nell Blaine Papers 1945-1999, undated
Special Collections and Archives, James Branch Cabell Library
M 67
1.5 linear feet.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
The Nell Blaine Papers are made up of four donations including materials donated by Maurice Bonds and Theresa Pollak in 1987; unprocessed materials that were discovered with the original manuscript collection that have an unconfirmed provenance; materials donated by John Bryan in the 1990s; and items collected by Janice Ritter McMurray, a graduate of Virginia Commonwealth University, donated in 2010.
Biographical Information
Nell Blaine (1922-1996) was a prominent American painter. Blaine was born in Richmond, Virginia and attended the Richmond Professional Institute from 1939-42. She studied under prominent artists such as Theresa Pollak (1899-2002) and Worden Day (1915-1986). In 1942-43, she received a grant from the Virginia Museum of Fine Arts to study under the renowned abstract expressionist, Hans Hofmann (1880-1966). Her art grew out of the Abstract Expressionist Movement of the 1940s. Her vast array of work, which spans half a century, encompasses indoor scenes, landscapes, and still lifes. Her work appears in many major American collections including the Virginia Museum of Fine Arts, the Museum of Modern Art, and the Whitney Museum of American Art, among others.
Even though Blaine relocated permanently to Manhattan, New York in the 1940s, she exhibited frequently in Richmond. The Richmond Times-Dispatch extolled her success throughout her career, recalling her roots as a Richmond native. Blaine traveled extensively in Europe, the Caribbean, and South America to paint and to find inspiration. While staying in Greece in 1959, she contracted spinal bulbar polio. The disease left her paralyzed from the waist down for the rest of her life. She continued painting and exhibiting until the 1990s. Not only does Blaine's art contribute to American painting but she leaves a legacy for the Richmond art community.
For more information, consult the following sources:
Longaker, Jon D. "Blaine Works Shown Here." Richmond Times-Dispatch. September 9, 1962, 8.
McVetta, Lee Ryan. "A Stylistic Analysis of Rhythm in Nell Blaine's Painting: 1942-1959." Master's thesis, Virginia Commonwealth University, 1996.
Sawin, Martica. Nell Blaine: Her Art and Life. New York: Hudson Press, 1998.
Scope and Content
The Nell Blaine Papers, 1945-1999, are significant because the collection provides foundational research materials on Nell Blaine's career and contribution to American art. The three most common materials in the collection are articles and newspaper clippings, exhibition brochures, and correspondence from Nell Blaine.
Series I, donated by Maurice Bonds and Theresa Pollak, contains five folders. Articles and newspaper clippings from 1961-1973 and exhibition catalogs spanning 1970-1999 are key primary source materials. Series I also contains an academic paper about Nell Blaine from 1971 by VCU alumni, Janice Ritter (now Janice Ritter McMurray).
Series II contains four folders that have an unconfirmed provenance. The series contains a 1972 agenda calendar that features Nell Blaine's art in the month of January. There are also black and white photographs of Nell Blaine's work that date between 1959-1975. The articles and exhibitions, ranging from 1945-1978, are grouped together based on the original order of donation.
Series III includes ten folders that were donated by John Bryan in the 1990s. Half of the collection contains correspondence from Nell Blaine to Mr. and Mrs. Hal Clark between 1971-1995. The articles and newspaper clippings were collected by the Clarks between 1948-1993. The two folders of postcards were probably sent from Nell Blaine to the Clarks-she often attached blank postcards to her letters highlighting the places she visited or artists she admired.
Series IV consists of eight folders donated in 2010 by Janice Ritter McMurray, a former student at Virginia Commonwealth University. She originally compiled materials for an art history class in 1970 but she continued to collect exhibition brochures and newspaper clippings until 1992. McMurray had travelled to Blaine's studio in New York to conduct an interview and they remained friends for many years afterward. Two important papers written by McMurray are also in the collection. First, is an undated reflective paper that summarizes McMurray's involvement with Blaine. A second important paper from McMurray is her draft from the 1970 class, which contains a note with suggestions from Blaine herself. A copy of the final paper has been attached to the draft. The original paper appears in Series I, Folder 2. The letters McMurray received from Blaine between1969-1972 are also in the collection. A set of blank stationary designed by Blaine give a glimpse into her art. Photographs from 1968 also show Blaine's work in progress.
Arrangement
The Nell Blaine Papers, 1945-1999, are divided into four series. Series I, donated by Maurice Bonds and Theresa Pollak, was originally compiled in 1987. In February 2011, three other series were added. Series II comprises of unprocessed materials that were discovered with M 67 and has an unconfirmed provenance. Series III was originally unprocessed materials from M 5 The Theresa Pollak Papers, 1917-1996, which were donated by John Bryan in the 1990s. Series IV was collected by Janice Ritter McMurray, a graduate of Virginia Commonwealth University, and donated in 2010.
Contents List
- The Maurice Bonds and Theresa Pollak Collection of Nell Blaine Materials 1961-1999, undated (Box 1)
  - Articles and newspaper clippings 1961-1973 (Box-folder 1:1)
  - Biographical Materials undated (Box-folder 1:2)
  - Correspondence 1995-1996 (Box-folder 1:3)
  - Exhibit brochures 1970-1999 (Box-folder 1:4)
  - Original academic paper by Janice Ritter 1971 (Box-folder 1:5)
- Nell Blaine Materials 1945-1978 (Box 2)
  - Articles and Exhibit Brochures 1945-1969 (Box-folder 2:6)
  - Articles and Exhibit Brochures 1970-1978 (Box-folder 2:7)
  - Peace Calendar featuring Nell Blaine's art 1972 (Box-folder 2:8)
  - Photographs of Nell Blaine's art 1959-1975 (Box-folder 2:9)
- The John Bryan Collection of Nell Blaine Materials 1948-1995 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence to Mr. and Mrs. H.B. Clark 1971-1976 (Box-folder 3:10)
  - Correspondence to Mr. and Mrs. H.B. Clark 1977-1980 (Box-folder 3:11)
  - Correspondence to Mr. and Mrs. H.B. Clark 1981-1985 (Box-folder 3:12)
  - Correspondence to Mr. and Mrs. H.B. Clark 1986-1990 (Box-folder 3:13)
  - Correspondence to Mr. and Mrs. H.B. Clark 1991-1995 (Box-folder 3:14)
  - Miscellaneous Nell Blaine papers 1986-1991 (Box-folder 3:15)
  - Mr. and Mrs. H.B. Clark postcard collection undated (Box-folder 3:16)
  - Nell Blaine postcard collection 1975-1992 (Box-folder 3:17)
  - Newspaper Clippings 1948-1993 (Box-folder 3:18)
  - Photographs by Nell Blaine 1993-1994 (Box-folder 3:19)
- The Janice McMurray Collection of Nell Blaine materials 1949-1992, undated (Box 4)
  - Articles and newspaper clippings 1960-1992, undated (Box-folder 4:20)
  - Correspondence from Nell Blaine to Janice Ritter McMurray 1969-1972, undated (Box-folder 4:21)
  - Draft of academic paper from Richard Carlyon's class with comments from Blaine 1970 (Box-folder 4:22)
  - Exhibit Brochures 1949-1992 (Box-folder 4:23)
  - Janice Ritter McMurray's reflective paper on Nell Blaine undated (Box-folder 4:24)
  - Letter of recommendation from four distinguished people in American art undated (Box-folder 4:25)
  - Photographic collection 1968 (Box-folder 4:26)
  - Stationary designed by Nell Blaine undated (Box-folder 4:27)